[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
here's space let's concentrate on space
no energy
around we can take space time to be flat
but in particular if space time is is
flat it's just ordinary manowski space
we can certainly imagine that base is
flat by slicing through it in a in a
flat way but now let's put a particle
into it if we put a particle into
it particles have energy and the right
hand side is no longer zero at the point
where the particle is and only at the
point where the particle is there's
curvature can you think of a geometry
which has the
property that it is not everywhere
except at a
point a
cone yes so the
solution of the problem of general
relativity of a point
mass is that space is a
cone and of course there's also
time space time if we want to think
about it we could think about it this
way time goes up
and space instead of being just flat it
is just flat but right where the
particle
is there's a
conical deficit a deficit angle just
like when we make a cone by cutting out
with a scissor a piece of deficit
angle okay now how big would you think
the deficit angle is well if there's no
particle then there's no deficit
angle what if there's a particle of mass
m what would you
think proportional to M exactly so
that's exactly right the deficit angle
here is proportional to M but the
deficit and in fact it doesn't have to
be a particle it could be any
distribution of
energy that's
bounded it won't be exactly a cone but
outside the region where that energy is
it'll have the same geometry as a cone
so it might be a cone with a sort of
rounded surface to it but that's not so
important all right now then comes the
question how big does this Mass have to
be before the deficit
angle is 360° there's nothing left when
the uh when the deficit angle is
360° the space has essentially
disappeared what has happened is it's
closed up into a uh thank you
Michael the cone has
gotten narrower and
narrower the deficit angle eventually
goes to the point where there's no cone
left at first it started as a big flat
cone when the particle at the center was
light as the particle got heavier and
heavier the cone shrunk until there was
no cone left there's a maximum amount of
mass that you can put into three
dimensions before it closes up and just
uh uh closes up and disappears how big
is that mass not very big the plunk
Mass so so we are not going the it's the
only mass in the problem
so well we we
no it's a dust
grain right so at most you could have uh
in the way of life in three dimensions
you could have a single
microorganism not much room to uh to
develop an intelligence not and so forth
and so on
so space of two Dimensions is clearly
ruled out space of one dimension turns
out to be even
worse uh gravity in one dimension one
dimension space one dimension of time is
so sick that it's not even worth
thinking about uh three dimensions three
space dimensions one time Dimension
gravity behaves in the usual way what
happens when you go to four four
dimensions well it's not just gravity
it's gravity and also um
electromagnetism which is sick now first
of all I'll tell you in what way gravity
is gravity is not so much sick and four
dimensions four when I when I speak
about Dimensions I'm speaking about
spatial
Dimensions uh in four dimensions four
plus one Dimensions gravity is
reasonably
healthy but there is there are some
dynamical features to it which make it
awkward uh the solar system would not be
stable the solar system would be very
chaotic this is just a particular fact
about Dimensions higher than three that
the Newtonian Force law or the force law
that would derive out of Einstein's
equations uh has bad instabilities and
so the solar system would be very
chaotic and the result of that is it
probably wouldn't take very long before
the planet got ejected out of orbit but
things are much worse than that that's
not the worst thing that by by no means
the worst thing in yeah do you
get no you don't get one over R squ
that's why it's that's why it's funny
you get one over R
cubed as you go up in Dimensions it goes
from 1 R 2 to 1 R Cub to 1 R to 4th now
the real problem has to do with atoms
electrons are little solar
systems and it's not just gravity which
goes from 1 R 2 to 1 R cubed and so
forth uh electromagnetism also does it's
governed by the same kind of force
law uh kum's law Newton's law have the
same form and that's true in every
Dimension so what happens as you go in
higher Dimensions is the attractive
force of gravity becomes stronger and
stronger at small distances 1 / R
cubed let's compare 1 / R cubed with 1 /
R 2
on r s excuse
me
uh this is the force LW when there are
fource space dimensions this is the
force law when there are three space
dimensions well if I were to
just I'm afraid we're going to run out
of ink tonight 1 / R squar let's first
plot 1 / r s now is 1 / R squar bigger
is one of R Cub bigger or smaller than
one of r
squared it's not well defined I have to
tell me where at R equals 1 they're
exactly the
same at R bigger than one R SAR is of
course the
larger
yes so one of R cubed is smaller but at
small
r 1 / R cubed is
bigger so so one can expect then that
the force law holding atoms together
will be weaker at large distances but
much smaller at small distances the
effect would first of all be the long
distance kulum Force which holds the
outer electrons in place would be much
weaker and there would not be uh veence
electrons and so forth they would just
fly off they would uh they would uh fly
on the other hand the inner electrons
would be pulled in much more tightly in
fact in four space dimensions the the
kulum law when combined with quantum
mechanics would pull the electrons right
into the nucleus so there wouldn't be
atoms without atoms there is no
chemistry it only gets worse in five
dimensions and six dimensions and so
forth so we don't know really what y
four dimensions what we do know is we
couldn't be sitting
here if the number of Dimensions was
higher yeah so is the number of
Dimensions that the nuclear forces are
seeing larger again so is the number of
dimensions in which the nuclear forces
larger and they
exibit I didn't understand you you asked
me something about the nuclear force
right or strong force they would also be
uh Stronger at small
distances and would
probably do real
damage um to the theory of uh um quirks
and lepon quarks in particular theory of
quirks would not bind together properly
into uh into protons and neutrons I
concentrated on atoms but much of what I
said you could also say about uh the
forces that held quarks together and so
forth so it would be
bad um and besides it's not entirely
clear that topologically that sex is
possible in higher
Dimensions this is
important longer and
longer can you say anything about three
spatial dimensions and two time
Dimensions no that that just boggles a
mind I don't know how to think about a
world with more than than one time
Dimension
that's
no seems like got three time Dimensions
toch theal
Dimensions yeah syry it's not clear
right it really isn't clear how to think
about what it would mean to have more
than one time
Dimension um it's so
confusing that um
no I have nothing to say about it right
now okay so
um four dimensions does seem to be
special as I said not for deep
mathematical reasons as far as we know
but there are certain features of basic
physics which seem to work in four
dimensions which uh for one reason or
another seem to be very thorny and
problematic atoms stabil of the solar
system uh the fact that in three
dimensions you can't have more than a
plunk worth of mass before you close the
universe up into a infinitely narrow
cone so forth and so
on
uh any other
question on the same thing why does time
deserve dimensional
St well that I don't know what that
means um
it's a dimensional status mean why do we
call it a dimension yeah well why
not well the real reason we call it a
dimension is because of Einstein who
whose special theory of relativity mixes
space and time together with
Transformations that uh that um
resemble mathematically rotations of
space in other words there are
transformation ations which mix space
and time together so it uh it becomes
natural to think of time as a dimension
of A four-dimensional
Spacetime uh there's no unique in four
dimension in in space and time there is
no unique time
axis perpendicular to a space axis a
moving reference frame as a Time axis
which points in some other direction the
corresponding space is also tilted so
there's no uniqueness to what the time
axis is and they get mixed up with each
other and it's quite profitable the
mathematical structure of the theory
space and time come in Fairly
symmetrically
app for example and energy and momentum
are time and space components of four
vectors so
last last week I think you said you
would show us where the cosmological
constant went into the equation yeah
yeah are that's part of the the lecture
you're planning or I actually hadn't but
I'll tell you right
now the question is more interesting
question is what does the cosmological
constant do but first let me tell you
where it goes in the
equations let's remember what's in the
equations
on the left hand side we have something
that involves
geometry I told you that the only
tensors that we can make out of the
gravitational
field uh that have two indices remember
on the right hand side we're going to
have the energy momentum tensor two
indices the only simple tensors that can
be constructed or the simplest ones are
r
knew and whether I put the indices
upstairs or downstairs doesn't matter
you canow raise them lower them same
thing arm you new
and minus some constant whether it's
minus or plus we figure out later uh G
muu times
R now that's not quite right the
coefficient here is determined deter
determined by requiring well let we're
going to we're going to put on the right
hand side T muu times a numerical
constant 8 Pi * the Newton constant but
sometimes just called
K uh we expect and hope that energy
momentum will be
conserved that means that the covariant
derivative Del mu of T mu new a kind of
continuity equation for each component
momentum and energy a separate
continuity equation for each and if
that's true then it had better be that
the leftand side also satisfies the same
thing incidentally to make it satisfy
the same thing we'd have to put the
indices upstairs but that's no big deal
and what Einstein discovered is
that very
generally no special assumptions about
the geometry if he put a half here then
in fact the left hand side
satisfies let's see this this tensor as
it stands is called g muu g for gravity
or if we put the indices
upstairs gunu it automatically satisfies
for any
geometry this
identity so that fixed the form of
Einstein's equations with one ambiguity
there is one more tensor that you can
form out of the metric which has the
property which has this property this
property is called covariant
conservation there's one more tensor
that you can form and that tensor is
just the metric
itself the metric
itself
satisfies Del
mu G mu new is equal to
zero it's
equivalent to the statement no uh uh yes
that's correct why is that the reason is
because the coari all covariant
derivatives of the metric tensor are
zero the metric tensor is the one tensor
whose covariant derivatives are all zero
one way to see that is to go to a
reference
frame where the the metric and all of
its derivatives are equal to zero we
talked about such a frame you can always
choose coordinates where the metric is
constant the constant simply means its
first derivatives are equal to zero that
means the christopal symbols are zero if
the metric has no derivatives and the
christopal symbols are equal to zero
then the covariant derivative of the
metric must be exactly equal to zero the
covariant derivative all covariant
derivative IES of the metric are equal
to zero but in particular the one which
corresponds to this continuity
equation from here to here is just
replacing little G by Big
G
uh it's also true so that means there's
one more
thing that we could have added into the
left hand side here plus some constant
any
constant lamb
time g
muu equals K T
muu what's that
oh can't do that can you that's that's
illegal
right that's the one ambiguity that
Einstein discovered in his equations
Lambda is called the cosmological
constant it can be positive or
negative and we'll talk about it what it
actually corresponds to is a
modification of the uh gravitational
force Law And depending on the sign of
Lambda it either adds an attraction or a
repulsion but it's an attraction or
repulsion which is quite different than
the Newtonian Force law it's a force
which grows with distance instead of f =
1 / R2 it's F proportional to
R
so we're going to talk about this later
but for the time being it's just an
ambiguity that was in Einstein's
equations the numerical value of Lambda
was known to be extremely small Einstein
and everybody else at the time and for
many many years thought that there must
be a reason
why this is not there nobody knew any
reason for it we know now that it is
there with a very small coefficient so
this is called a cosmological constant
but for the most part we're going to
talk about the theory without
cosmological constant at least until we
get to
cosmology the reason is that the
cosmological constant is so small that
the repulsive force that it creates is
completely insignificant on until you go
out to distances which are cosmological
and uh until you go out to distances of
tens of
uh uh tens of billions of light years or
billions of Light Years anyway yeah
would it be fair to say that the first
equation you start out by getting there
by you know some kind of tensor analysis
of things that might work then you have
to you must have to verify that this
equation but you have to verify with
experiments I mean that equation is not
dered first principles is this equation
yes this
equation equation oh this equation here
no this is all right so let's go back a
step what Einstein was looking to do was
to convert to tensor notation equations
which in certain
limits reproduced Newton's
equations it was a guess not that he had
to reproduce Newton's equations in those
limits but the right thing to do was to
look for tensor
equations uh equations which would be
true in any reference
frame the left the right hand side here
for very very slowly moving masses and
weak gravitational fields the right hand
side
here is only
significant when you have two indices
zero 0 0 component and then it becomes
the energy density the energy density on
the right hand side here with this
Kappa on the left hand
side if you make the approximation that
the metric is not very distorted from
the flat space form that it's close to
the flat space
form and if you assume that the metric
of a static object like a sun or
something like that uh is stat itic and
doesn't change with time then it's not
hard to show that r that r0 0 what we're
going to do is take the 0 0 component of
this equation 0 0 that means energy
density on the right hand side and on
the left hand side you work it out but
what you find out is that it's
proportional to some second derivative
derivative with respect to
x m
squared space derivatives purely space
derivatives in fact we can write it in
the form
of Del squ it's got two derivatives in
it of what of G KN now I'm probably
missing a factor of two I always get the
factor of two confused but if you
remember G not was very closely related
to the Newtonian potential
so this just became the equation uh the
llas equation or whatever it's called
aone equation connecting the
gravitational potential with
row
uh did he derive this equation from
first
principles um no he used a
correspondence with Newtonian
gravity he made an assumption the
Assumption being that the equations
should have the same form in every
reference frame this was a big deal for
Einstein he felt deep in his heart that
the that equation should have the same
form in every reference frame you can't
prove that you can postulate it and see
what you get what you
got was a tensor version of Newtonian uh
mechanics which would be true if it were
true in any frame would be true in every
frame now it has of course empirical
consequences
it's not exactly Newton's Theory it
differs in various contexts its
empirical uh consequences are different
when things move fast or when matter or
the material that's gravitating is so
dense that it creates very powerful
gravitational fields then it doesn't
Newton and Einstein don't really agree
and there Einstein wins
empirically so
uh right you're you're perfectly right
this didn't uh this wasn't
entirely just out of pure air it came
from looking for a particular
realization of tensor version of
Newton's equations now
um let's
before before we study particular
Solutions of these
equations particular the Schwarz Shield
solution which is a black
hole uh before we enter into that which
I want to at least start to do
tonight I want to talk about the way
physicists today think about the
equivalence
principle um remember I showed you how
Einstein thought about light falling he
thought about light Falling by saying
light in an ordinary reference from
frame and an inertial reference frame
moves in straight lines if it moves in
straight lines in an inertial frame then
in an accelerated frame remember the
elevator there's the elevator if it's
accelerated upward then from inside the
accelerator the light beam will seem to
fall he wanted to generalize that idea
that was a very simple idea good enough
for a simple version of elevator physics
but he wanted to do much better than
that what he realized is that the
equivalence principle what it
said was first of all that physics
should be the same in all reference
frames that the the the the equation
frames but beyond
that he said if you choose coordinates
now you can only do this locally
remember you can't do this over the
whole Space but if locally you choose
coordinates which in which the metric is
just equal to the metric of special
relativity in other words if you work
with coordinates which locally for which
gunu is
equal to ad youu which is just equal to
1 - one - one -
one then in the vicinity of that
point the equation of physics should
have the same form that they have in
special
relativity so here's what he said he
said if we know equations in special
relativity we can take those
equations and try to make tensor
equations out of them so that they will
be true in any coordinate system and
once we have those equations in tensor
form then we can just take them over as
they are into situations where space
might really be
curved so what he was in in effect
saying is that on small enough volumes
small enough regions of SpaceTime where
curvature can't be detected same like
the surface of the Earth a small patch
of the surface of the Earth you can't
detect
curvature the motion of balls rolling on
the surface of the Earth and so forth
for small patches looks exactly like the
motion of balls moving on a flat plane
that's what Einstein said he said in
SpaceTime if you study regions of
SpaceTime which are small enough so
that uh so that curvature is not
important then the equation should have
the same form that they have in special
relativity let's take the equations from
special
relativity and do something to them so
that they become tensor equations and
then we'll know what equations should be
in general relativity just the same
tensor equations let me give you an
example uh we've already done that with
the motion of
particles what's the law of motion of a
particle in an inertial reference
frame well let's let's Suppose there are
no forces acting on the particle right
no electric no magnetic forces just a a
force free
particle it moves in a straight line
with a constant velocity that's the same
thing as saying it moves in a straight
line through through SpaceTime moves in
a straight line through
SpaceTime Einstein's generalization of
that is that particles move on the
straightest possible lines lines which
locally look like they're going straight
ahead and that meant
geodesics he didn't have to invent a
force law he simply said I'll I'll take
what I know from particles moving
without any gravitational forces on them
that they move in perfectly straight
lines and I will say locally along the
trajectory as long as curvature is not
important they'll just move Straight
Ahead exactly as if they were in flat
space uh and that became his principle
particles move on
geodesics from that we were able to
deduce the equation of motion for
particles
the geodesic equation of motion and
relate it to uh to Newton's equation for
the motion of a particle in a field of
acceleration all right let me I want to
go through another example and show you
how it works wave
motion uh we could use Maxwell's
equations but Maxwell's equations are a
little bit complicated so let's take the
wave motion of a simpler field than
electric and magnetic fields a scal
field last quarter when we did a little
bit of um study of field Theory we
talked about the structure in special
relativity of a scalar wave equation was
it last quarter I think some number of
quarters ago right maybe it was a half
maybe it was a half ago maybe it was
three4 ago I don't remember but we
did uh talk about wave equation
wave equations in special relativity
let's write down the wave equation in
special relativity for a Scala field and
then see what we can do to turn it into
a general relativity
equation all right so let's start with
waves moving up and down one dimension
with the speed of light right uh
sometimes I'll use the speed of light
equal to one sometimes I won't for the
moment let's let the speed of light be
General anybody remember what the
equation of motion of a wave looks like
a wave equation for moving up and down a
line it's got a field let's call the
field
fi just on a one-dimensional axis to
begin
with well it has some derivatives of fi
time derivatives of fi and space
derivatives of
fi and the form of the equation is that
the second derivative of f with respect
to time
s this is the simplest possible wave
equation uh that that is
equal to the second derivative of f with
respect to let's call the space
coordinate
X that no that's not quite right if we
put the speed of light in uh let's see
um I think we have to put uh c^2 here is
that right yeah c^ squ here then that
describes waves
two kinds of waves waves which can move
to the left or waves which can move to
the
right and the shape of the wave stays
fixed that describes waves which move
sort of rigidly down the axis preserving
their shape either to the left or to the
right those are the two kinds of ways of
course you can and you can have
superpositions of them you can have wave
you can have one wave moving to the
right another wave moving to the left
and what'll happen is they'll just pass
right through each other that's the wave
equation in one spatial Dimension now
supposing I want my wave to be moving
not along the x- axis but along the Y
AIS what do I do well I just substitute
y for
X what if I want my wave moving in a
general
axis what do I have to do to this wave
equation to describe the general kind of
wave that can propagate in three spatial
dimensions and the answer is simple you
just
add DC 5 by dy^
2 plus DC F by dz^2
if I set c equal to 1 now let's set c
equal to
one uh so that we go back to
our uh notation that we're that we
become familiar with we set that equal
to 1 we can then write this in the form
the second derivative of
f with respect to X
mu watch what I'm going to
do X
New
Times
AA mu
new equals z
let's see why that is remember what a to
mu new is its time time component is
one that means and of course this is
contracted summed over mu and new all
right let's start with mu and new equal
to zero in other words the time time
component then what we'll get is the
second derivative of five with respect
to
t^2 X not is the same as T so
Ada that's 1 time second derivative of I
with respect to T with respect to T
again that's just second partial of I
with respect to
t^2 now what about ada1 one first of all
the off diagonal terms are zero Ada just
remind you what Ada is Ada is the
Matrix 1 - one - one - one it has no off
diagonal elements so there are no terms
here in which for example contain a
derivative with respect to x times a
derivative with respect to y or
derivative sub T time no mixed ones all
right now what
about 8011 what is 8011 8011 is minus
one so let's see what we have from a to
n n we have second I with respect to
t^2 and now what about a to11 that's
minus1 and it becomes second partial ofi
with respect to X1
squared what about a to
22 same
thing plus the third
term well that's just
this in particular if I transpose this
to the other side and set it equal to
zero we've written the wave equation in
what looks like a nice tensor form but
is it a tensor form it is not we have
not yet succeeded in making a tensor
equation we've succeeded in making a
nice formula but it's not a tensor
equation so let's see why let's see what
this says more carefully do it in two
pieces
first of all Adam
youu uh is um not a general tensor form
but we might just want to replace this
by
gunu that we might uh that we can do all
right so gunu we might put gunu
here that looks more tensor is but it's
still not a tensor equation and the
reason is because these are not
covariant
derivatives let's start let's write it
this way we have g
muu
d by let's start with DX
new now I have obviously not written the
thing that's up above but let's multiply
it by D by DX
mu well that's clearly not the same as
the thing I've written
here
uh why because first of
all G depends on position so when I
differentiate I'll get one term with a
derivative of G mu new and another term
of just the type that I have here so I
haven't re first of all this is not
necessarily A tensor equation and second
of all it's not this
okay but before I differentiate it with
respect to X mu let's erase this for a
moment and let's forget G mu new is this
a tensor d by DX
new yes the derivative of a scalar is a
vector so the first step
here is a good tensor what happens if I
multiply it by G mu new
is
it still a tensor yeah it's a tensor Now
with an upstairs index instead of a
downstairs index now what happens if I
differentiate and what what is it it
it's a tensor but it's a vector in
particular a vector with one
contravariant
index now what happens if I try to
differentiate it d by
DX mu
is it a tensor
now no what do I have to do to make it a
tensor take the covariant derivative
incidentally I started with this
equation
here I could have taken the D by DX mu
outside remember Ada is a constant a
bunch of constants you can differentiate
a or not differentiate a it doesn't make
any
difference uh but but this as it stands
is not a
tensor incidentally how many in with
tensor or not how many exposed indices
does it
have
zero mu combines with this mu and new
combines with this new so if it were a
tensor which it is not what kind of
tensor would it
be a scaler but this is not the right
rule for making a scaler out of a vector
we have to replace this
by covariant derivative so we have to
add to it
plus
gamma mu let's let's call this object
here this is a vector let's call it V
mu uh yes let's call it V mu we're
covariant differentiating V mu with
respect to X mu and so that means we
have to Let's see we have to put another
mu here a
new and a V new I
believe which is just let's see if I've
got it
right uh and
V is
defi I'm messing this up let's let's go
back you want the partial on the first
one and the
gam that that's right we want partial on
the first one and then gamma
mu yeah V is the whole thing so then I
should put
V mu
right gamma mu no let's see I don't have
it right we have to put some indices
into the gamma here uh
gamma
Mu Alpha
Alpha I think I have it right
now yeah the derivative with respect to
X
mu gets replaced by a gamma
mu the index mu is upstairs here and an
alpha and a v Alpha here but then V
Alpha is what it is
G Alpha
Beta d by DX beta
all right that's the covariant
derivative we could write this in a very
simple form Del mu covariant derivative
of G mu new DF by DX
new that's what it is but to work out
what the covariant derivative is means
there some christopal symbols
this is a more complicated
equation than the equation that we
started with but it's a tensor
equation
this is the wave
equation in curved
coordinates in fact it's a wave equation
in curved coordinates whether or not the
space is flat it's a tensor equation if
it's true in one frame of reference it's
true in every frame of reference
and this yeah is it zero yeah it's equal
to
zero
so all Einstein did was he took the
standard wave equation Maxwell's
equations rewrote them in curvy linear
coordinates and then said I'm going to
insist that I rewrite them in a form in
which they have a tensor form so that if
they're true in one coord system they're
true in every coordinate system right
and how do they do it basically the same
rule replace ordinary derivatives by
covariant derivatives that's all replace
ordinary derivatives by covariant
derivatives and that will give you uh
your equation now the new
equation is more complicated and notice
in the equation the gravitational field
appears
remember what gamma was gamma played the
role of a kind of gravitational
force when it was applied to the motion
of a particle gamma had things like the
derivatives of uh the Newtonian
potential in it so what appears over
here is a kind of gravitational
force and the wave equation
contains not only
what you might have expected namely some
second derivatives of fi but it contains
another term and that other term is
actually the gravitational force on the
wave field
itself
so that's
how ordinary simple waves would interact
with a gravitational field the effect of
this of course is to bend waves this is
a function of
position uh the wave equation now has a
form form in which the various
coefficients are position dependent do
you know any situation in which a wave
equation has position dependent
coefficients of various
kinds yeah varying density varying um
dialectric constant and so forth and
what is the effect of varying uh density
or dialectric
constant it well in particular it can B
the
wave it can bend the wave when light
enters water non
perpendicularly the wave is bent due to
the variation with respect to space of
um of a particular coefficient in the
wave equation here there are various
coefficients in the wave equation these
depend on
position and the effect is among other
things to bend waves change their
frequency do various things to them that
wouldn't happen in empty space waves
don't just propagate along and straight
lines anymore they Bend they refract or
whatever the right words are uh refract
is that the right word which is
refract refract is what happens when
water goes when yeah yeah right right
okay
so this is what's called the equivalence
principle namely the way you derive the
laws of physics and gravitational field
is to take the laws of physics without
the gravitational field and just convert
them to tensor
form that's
all and uh and then the christopal
symbols and the metric and so forth then
determine how the gravitational field
affects the motion of waves or whatever
you have all right so here
then um just one technical question here
just make sure I understand that c
symbol the gamma
has upstairs and downstairs
right gamma has me upstairs and
downstairs yeah it has me upstairs and
downstairs let's see why I
think yeah yeah the gamma has mu
upstairs and me downstairs and then an
extra index Alpha which combines with v
Alpha
and then I just wrote that V
Alpha so at the heart of all this is
[Music]
Einstein
right and more than that and more than
that that locally in little
patches in which uh which are too small
for the curvature to be felt they should
behave exactly as if there was no uh
gravitational field right so it's a
little more than just what you
said and a little more is the content of
the uh equivalence
principle do coari differentiation a
product have
the rule MH right so why I mean if you
just write that in terms of coari
derivatives the the G mu new goes
outside doesn't it yes it does yeah so
let's just write it in terms of
covariant
derivatives yeah an obvious thing to
write is that first of all at d by DX
mu is just Del
mufi for ordinary derivatives of a
scalar okay and then what we had was G
mu new
Del
new that's basically what I wrote the D
muf that was just ordinary derivative
multiply by G mu new of X and then take
the covariant derivative of what's in
here but then as you correctly point out
covariant derivatives satisfy the liet
rule the livets rule being that a
covariant derivative of a * B is equal
to covariant derivative of a * B
B plus a * covariant derivative of
B all right so the covariant derivative
of G times this is just two terms the
first is G mu new of x * Del new Del mu
of
Y and the second involves the covariant
derivative of G muu but what's the
covariant derivative of G
muu zero so this is it this is the form
of the wave
equation but the reason I wrote it in a
more complicated way is I wanted to make
very explicit how the spatial variations
of G muu and the christofel symbols
enter into the equation and
effectively make it almost as though the
curvature oface SpaceTime was a kind of
variable material that light was moving
through that's not quite uh true but
sort of like that causes like to bend
among other things all right
um now good so that that told
Einstein how to figure out the effect of
gravity on things that he already knew
about the next question is how do the
things that he knew about affect
gravity that's equivalent in this
context it's equivalent to asking the
question supposing I have a scal of
field that satisfies such an equation
with such a property what do I put on
the right hand
side the right hand side is energy and
momentum light has energy light has
momentum scale of wave Fields have
energy and momentum so if I wanted to
make a nice little closed system of
gravity interacting with a wave
field here I've told you how gravity
affects the wave
field now I have to tell you how the
wave field affects
gravity okay so let's see if we can
figure that
out let's we're trying to do is tie up
the ends we have wave equations here F
fori but we still need to figure out
what goes on the right hand
side if we want to figure out how the
wave field affects
gravity all right so that uh there many
many ways to do this some
sophisticated some not so
sophisticated and we're not going to be
sophisticated tonight
we want an energy momentum
tensor that's made up out of fi now
let's begin by forgetting gravity
altogether and just imagine special
relativity in other words flat
SpaceTime and let's see if we can figure
out something about the energy momentum
tensor of a wave
field no gravity yet just ordinary flat
SpaceTime special relativity we have a
field F and now we can go back to the uh
we can go back to ordinary cartisian
coordinates in other words um minkowski
coordinates and write the wave equation
in the way that we had it
before uh it really can be written well
we can write it
as uh what did we have
before ad muunu
no Ada super mu new D mu d new pi equal
Z
right that was the wave equation written
in a nice covariant notation but in flat
space no christofel symbols no varying
metric just ad
youu can we guess what the energy
momentum tensor for f is well first of
all it has to be a tensor so it has to
be a thing with two indices what can we
do to F to create and give it some
indices to give to give an
expression involving fi that would have
some indices well we can differentiate
it
okay I'm interested in a thing with two
indices let's say team you new
so what can I make I can make things
like the
mui
DUI that's something I can make what
else I can add in Ada
muu we're in flat space time now I can
add in a
muu uh times
um times let's call it the
sigi D Sigma
fi anything else you can think
of staying away from
second second terms yeah okay why am I
staying away from second order
terms in other words you're asking why
couldn't I have things with two
derivatives such as the
muu right okay one of the terms I'm
using something that I already know that
I did teach you
previously uh let's see if uh if you
remember it anybody remember what the
energy of a wave field is just the
energy
what does the energy of a
wavefield
have what's
thate
ude take a look at this at this
expression what does it do if fi changes
sign
what happens to this expression if fi
changes its
sign it changes sign right it changes
sign that means if I take a wave
field which if this were in the energy
if this were in the energy then a wave
field which looks like this which might
have positive energy and a wave field
which look like this would not have the
same energy
a wave field which is in every respect
identical except the sign of five was
changed from five to Minus 5 would not
have the same
energy
um one would have yeah one would have
positive energy one would have negative
energy so one might expect then that
that is forbidden and it is
forbidden uh the energy should be
something which doesn't change sign when
you change F to Minus 5 it's like a
harmonic oscillator wave fields are very
much like harmonic oscillators harmonic
oscillators have coordinates X the
kinetic energy is X do sared the
potential energy is
x² if x changes sign nothing happens to
the energy the energy is positive
whether you pull the spring out to the
right or whether you pull the spring out
to the left the same is true of a violin
string a violin string is a good example
of a wave would you expect a wave which
looked like this to have opposite energy
from a wave which looks like this no you
wouldn't in fact they can go into each
other they can vibrate into each other
uh and so one expects on General grounds
that whatever the energy energy or in
the energy momentum of a field fi is
that it should not change sign when you
change the sign I now what happens to
this expression if F goes to Minus
5 nothing happens it stays the same
why
H because it's quadratic in the uh in F
IFI changes sign the mui changes sign
thei changes sign and the product
doesn't change sign so a term like this
is not expected in the energy momentum
tensor but these two terms terms are
perfectly good we can add them
together and we can add them together
with some unknown coefficient let's put
an unknown coefficient there what's a
good uh number what's a good letter for
an unknown
coefficient C thank
you
good now what I want to do is I want to
figure out if there's any value of C
which will
ensure
that
that the continuity equation is
satisfied
um the continuity
equation
is D super mu T mu new is equal to
zero now this is a funny looking
expression derivative you know what d
subm means
right that means derivative with respect
to X
mu and it's got a covariant index
downstairs all right d by DX
mu what does a deriv differential sign
like this mean with an upstairs
index you just raise the index what do
you use for the metric to raise the
index ad you
knew so this is a perfectly well-
defined symbol with an upstairs mu there
it just
means D super
mu equals Ada mu new d sub little
new the upstairs derivatives and the
downstairs derivatives are the same
thing except for some sign changes here
and there all right so this is the
continuity
equation or the conservation of energy
momentum in special relativity you can
push the indices upstairs and downstairs
I used to write it previously I wrote it
this way but it's the same thing indices
can be moved upstairs and downstairs at
will and here's my continuity
equation we can also write this equation
in Neer form we can just write Ada mu
new on D new just turns this into D mu D
mu V
one downstairs D mu one upstairs D mu
that's what the ad muu
does so here's what we have going for us
five satisfies that equation and we want
to find out if there's a linear
combination of these two which is
conserved if it is if there is it will
give us a candidate for the energy
momentum tensor in fact it's
Unique okay so let's just let's try it
out let's differentiate this super
mu T mu
new what do I get apply it to the right
hand side here that gives me D
mu D mu du new no d muf d newy
that's the first piece first term over
here all right now this is a product
liet's rule can be applied what do I get
I get D mu D mu
F times DUI that's one term and what's
the other
term the other term is plus d mui
D mu d new
F that's when the D mu here hits the
second term well what is this piece over
here that's zero that's the wave
equation so let's get rid of
it okay now
let's we still have this term over here
we still have to hit it with d mu D
mu constant C A to mu
new D Sigma f d Sigma
F what is that going to have well D
super mu a to mu new what is
that that's just d sub
new d sub
new what's it going to have it's going
to have a term with a d Sigma and then a
term with a mixed derivative d new D
Sigma there'll be two of
them can you see why there are two of
them one
from hitting here and one from hitting
here they're both the same you can
juggle these indices upstairs and
downstairs it doesn't cost anything so
there are two terms Each of which have
the form d new D Sigma
5times D
Sigma okay but this term is of exactly
the same form as
this a derivative of f
and then yeah if I replace let's see if
we replace Sigma by mu they're exactly
the same
thing but we get two of these
terms we get two of these
terms and
um that means I want the factor of two
someplace I want to let's see what are
we
doing
H yeah the question uh I I I know I
dropped but where did I drop
it
uh I think we want c equal a
half I think we want C equals a half
with c equal a half just go through this
go through it yourself with c equal a
half this becomes an identity that this
is equal to
zero that's an identity for all fi oh
for all fi which satisfy the wave
equation I use the wave equation
when I differentiated this term there
was one term which was D mu D muf that
was the wave equation then there was
another term and it canell
this it canel the two terms from here
that's why I had to put a half here all
right go through that it's a little
exercise not very hard if five satisfies
the wave equation then this object over
here satisfies the uh continuity
equation
let's
see do I want a minus
signus
sign let's compute now that we have it
and it's Unique there was no ambiguity
uh it's quite unique let's just see if
we can recognize what the energy density
is which terms the energy
density Z 0 does it matter whether the
whether they're upstairs or
downstairs it doesn't it doesn't when
you pull an upstairs index downstairs if
it's a Time index it doesn't change sign
if it's a space index it does change
sign but if we pull two time indices
downstairs then it certainly nothing
happens to it so the energy density is
either t or t subn KN same thing and
let's see what we
get all right we have mu and new both
being time so what is this I'm now going
to use the notation x no equals T time
so what is this term over
here just the square of the time der
dtive of
f not acceleration no it's just the
square of the time derivative of
f let's just call it f do
squared F do squ this is the energy
momentum
density sorry it's the density of energy
the density of energy F do squar that's
the first thing here dot meaning
derivative with respect to time and then
minus 12 and let's see what we have we
have Ada mu new so we're interested in
the time component of it what is Ada not
not one so we just leave that alone and
then we
have F do squared Yi do squared if Sigma
the sigma is the same as the sigma and
the sumova if Sigma is
time then raising and lowering doesn't
do
anything raising and lowering a Time
index doesn't change its sign raising
and lowering a space index does change
its sign so we have F dot * F
dot but then we also have the space
derivatives of fi here this could be X
then we would have derivative of fi with
respect to x s but with a plus sign or a
minus
[Music]
sign minus sign
because
811 sorry
because because pulling an index uh up
and down changes its sign and then same
thing with derivative of I with respect
to y^ squar minus derivative of 5 with
respect to z^
2 sorry D 5 with respect to Z
squ what do we get all together
we get 5 do^ 2 minus a half 5 do^
2 that's 5 do^ 2 over
two and
then the minus is here and the minus
here cancels each other and we get plus
the derivative of five with respect to
x^
squared plus the derivative of I with
respect to
Y squared plus the derivative of I with
respect to z^2 and I think I left out a
factor of a half multiplying each one of
these all times 1
12 what is this this is the kinetic
energy of the moving wave if we thought
of it as a violin string it would be the
kinetic energy of the violin string
and this is the energy the potential
energy in the violin string the
stretching of the violin string away
from its
equilibrium
uh when violin string is straight a
straight violin string has no potential
energy when the violin string has a
derivative then it has potential energy
so this is in fact the correct
expression for the energy
density we could also work out all the
other components of the energy momentum
tensor but why bother here it
is this is it you can go and figure out
all of its
components there is one
ambiguity the one
ambiguity is the overall coefficient in
front of it I could put a 10 in front of
it or a 100 in front of it and it would
still satisfy the continuity equation
where is it it would still satisfy the
continuity equation so there is an
ambiguity but that
ambiguity can and it is really there
it's it's ambiguous but you can always
absorb it into
the definition of fi supposing I decided
the energy momentum tensor should be 100
times this well then I could redefine fi
by taking five * 10 and calling it
something
new and then the new field were would
have an energy momentum tensor which
looked exactly like this so there's a
matter of convention there's a bit of a
matter of convention about the
definition of the field f it is always
defined so that the energy doesn't have
a factor of 100 or a factor of seven
it's defined in such a way that the
coefficient there is
one uh once you know it you can put it
into the right hand side of the
equations
here all right so you take this
now bodily bring it over to here
and it becomes the right hand side which
tells gravity how to respond to the
energy and momentum in the
wavefield yeah maybe it's a real naive
question but I I've read long ago that
pressure
uh has something to do with general
relativity
okay pressure
[Applause]
pressure is simply defined in terms of
the energy momentum tensor okay right
uh okay I'll tell you pressure is a
well-defined
thing when a gas or whatever it happens
to be is
isotropic if it's not isotropic
isotropic means you can't uh you know
the molecules are moving as much this
way as they are this way as they are
this way
uh when it's
isotropic if it's not isotropic then
there are different components of
pressure in the various axes and you
have to think about something a little
more complicated than pressure when a
gas or a material or a uh or whatever it
happens to be is
isotropic then the pressure is a
well-defined thing the same in every
direction and when the gas is isotropic
it means that the energy momentum tensor
it has a t knot here that's the energy
density but then it has nothing in the
off diagonals the off diagonals would
render it not isotropic and the only
elements it has are on the diagonal and
those are called the
pressure or are they minus the
pressure I think they're minus the
pressure oh uh the pressure or three
time or one/ third the pressure um no
they're the pressure
right so the pressure is just defined in
terms of the energy momentum
tensor anle off yeah yeah a sheer force
would be right right a sheer
force um a stress a sheer stress would
be uh uh would be an an a
non diagonal component but it would be
symmetric right
so you can see then that even in
isotropic situations the
pressure as well as the energy density
really does enter into uh into
Einstein's equations now when all the
C's C's meaning the speeds of light not
that uh not the C over there when the
speeds of light are put into the
equations the energy density is much
much larger than the pressure why
because energy density has c^ squ in
front of it so typically unless unless
you're in some
situation where there are things moving
with near the speed of light the energy
densities are usually much larger than
the pressure densities now for a box of
photons where everything is moving with
a speed of light pressures and energies
can be uh of the same order of magnitude
but in any case
um in any case yes pressure enters into
Einstein's equations as well as sheer
forces as well as what is a sheer force
a sheer force is if you have a block of
material and you try to Shear it you
know you try to push one edge of it one
way and the other edge of it the other
way that creates a kind of stress that
stress also enters into here it's uh
non-diagonal elements of
tmu so so uh yeah all right so that's in
fact that's one of the things that
Einstein discovered that energy momentum
and stress and pressure are all parts of
the source of the gravitational field
they all source of gravitational field
is it Beyond more than than it takes a
certain amount of energy to put let's
say pressure into volume and you could
just call that uh that equal to a mass
no it's more than that it is more than
that because it's off di um yeah for
example uh or for example if these
coefficients were not all equal to each
other different pressures in different
directions they might add up to a given
amount of energy but they would make the
gravitational field do things which were
different than if they are equal to each
other right
so that's uh the
basic idea of the equivalence
principle
um and you know like John Wheeler said
said well I'll just paraphrase what he
said
um energy and momentum tell the
gravitational field how to
bend and the gravitational
field well
we yeah let's write it correctly now Del
mu Del
mu which has all kinds of christopal
symbols and other things the
gravitational field tells the wave field
how to
propagate that's uh how to propagate
through space through the curved through
the curvature of space and how does it
do it it does it by christopal symbols
and metrics appearing within the
equations
here okay any questions up till now
yeah I think I see how you get an energy
momentum tensor from a potential from a
stress from from
from fluid motion from motion of charges
how do you get an energy momentum tensor
from a from a mass sitting somewhere
else from Mass a blob of mass over here
how do I know what the energy momentum
tensor is Einstein's equation exists at
every point in space right right it's a
point equation right but some energy
over here creates an energy over here it
doesn't create an energy over here I
have a mass here and mass is equivalent
energy so how do I
calculate all 16 terms of the stress of
the energy momentum tens are somewhere
else there
zero if there's energy over here and
only over here M yeah that's the energy
then the stress T then the energy
momentum tensor is non zero where the
mass is so space can't beur no no no no
no no no wait wait wait wait wait wait
wait that's two different
things let's go back a step let's go
back to Newton or not Newton but Newton
I'll appla some plus Newton plus and
plus is d^ 2 5
equals 4 Pi 4 Pi G
Row 4 Pi G row same equation is here at
least in the appropriate approximations
Del s f is R not or something like that
all right now supposing there's some
Mass someplace over here that's where
row is there's no row over here there's
no row over here there's no row over
here but does that mean that fi that
there is no fi over here no when you
solve this
equation you'll find that there's fi all
around this object over here how do you
see it well one way to remember it is to
use Gus's theorem to tell you that
there's a gravitational
field uh you know you use Gus's
theorem what this equation is telling
you is not that fi is zero out here but
that certain combinations of its
derivatives are zero out here the fact
that there's a
source determines a fi but it determines
a fi in a way in which this particular
expression vanishes outside and in fact
what does it do it leads to the 1 / R 2
or the 1/ r Force law one / R potential
energy law same thing here this may be
zero all over space except that a few
points but the curvature will be um will
be distributed over space in
general
question if light has energy and
momentum yeah then it affects space
curvature does that mean that light can
affect the propagation of light so they
interfering and don't obey superp
position yes very good question
example two light rays Crossing each
other what do you call lines which are
like this I forgot there's a word in
elementary geometry skew skew skew two
skew light rays going past each other uh
they they don't intersect but they would
intersect if they you know you know just
going past each other each one causes a
gravitational field which attracts the
other one so instead of just going I can
I do this let's
see they let's try they
so they attract each other you know what
I haven't they measured to very high
energy levels of the photons do not
interact with other photons yes yes yes
yes yes remember that Newton's constant
is
Tiny it is very very hard in a
laboratory to measure the gravitational
interaction between two
uh kilogram balls of
iron a photon or a light beam has very
very little energy and very very little
Mass it's energy divided by c^2 is its
mass and it's
remember it may be true that E
MC^2 but it's also true that m = e over
c^2 so if you have some
energy of an ordinary kind ordinary
magnitude the mass that it corresponds
to is
minute very very small if you then say
that the gravitational interaction
between these two things is their
effective let's write out what it would
be it would be their effective
masses this is terrible it would be
their effective masses M1
M2 times Newton's constant divided R 2 R
2 might be the distance of closest
approach of these two uh light waves now
what is M1 it's the
energy divided c^
2 e of Light Beam 1 time e of Light Beam
2 divided by C to the
4th C to the
4th C is 3 * 10 88th uh 10 17th 10- 34
in the
denominator 10-
34 and uh 7 * 10 -1 in the numerator
that's about 10 - 10 10 -
44 10-
44 time the energy / R 2 so in practice
of course the interaction between light
waves is entirely complete
negligible uh you never have enough
energy yeah a question on uh maybe
historical question on cosmological
concept what you what you read the
popular books is that Einstein was
compelled to put that in there to keep
the universe from collapsing yeah uh as
as opposed to
uh how you described it earlier where
where it fits right in in in in there
can you elaborate on that maybe yeah um
okay when we're at it let's talk about
the cosm let's talk about the
cosmological
constant okay so we modify the equations
r muu - 12 G mu new
R and then we add to it plus some Lambda
time G
muu and we set that equal to T
muu or k * t muu or
whatever um one can ask what is the
Newtonian analog of this and there is a
Newtonian analog of
it the right hand side of course is the
usual 4 Pi G * row as always the left
hand side has Del s
f and
then in
addition it just
has
plus Lambda now where did I get that
from I got this by looking at the NN
component of the equation on the left
hand side this whole object over here
it's nor nor component apart from a
factor of two or something is just d^ S
5 look at the NN component of this and
assume
that the gravitational fields are very
weak that means that g mu new is close
to the special relativity value the not
not component would be
one so Newton's
equations would get Modified by an extra
term okay now um this here represents if
I did if I just had no Lambda then the
equation is telling me how F out here
responds to the presence of a point
Mass but let's ask a different question
let's ask how
fi responds to just a cosmological
constant what is f like if there was a
cosmological constant with a Newtonian
all right can you find the solution of
this equation d^2 f is equal to Lambda
the sign of Lambda I'll figure out later
let's just uh let's be loose and sloppy
with the sign equals
Lambda uh I can find
it say it
again right right but but look at it
from this point of view it's equivalent
to just having a uniform mass density
it's equivalent to just put a uniform
mass density spread all over space now
what's the solution of this equation
it's not 5 equals 0 it's not 5 equals a
constant for I equals z or a constant
you would get uh zero on the left hand
side
yeah what if I took the function X2 +
y^2 + z^2
what's its Dell
squared it's a
number six
right differentiating X twice gives me
two y twice give me so this would be
six uh so I think I want to put a 1/ 6
Lambda and then d^ s of this if Y is
equal to this d^ s of 1 6 Lambda x^2 +
y^2 +
z^2 did I do that right no Lambda over 6
sorry Lambda over 6 that's
dumb Lambda over 6 X2 + y^2 + z^2 that
would be the solution of the equation
with just a uniform Lambda on the right
hand side now what does that mean
remember what fi is it's the
gravitational potential what do you do
with a
potential you differentiate it to
find the force so let's find the
components of force or the strictly
speaking the acceleration of an
object F has been defined in such a way
that its gradient is
acceleration all right so here we are we
have a a particle over here here's the
origin of
coordinates what is the X component of
force the X component of force
is the gradient of f along the x-axis or
maybe it's minus the gradient of f along
the
x-axis derivative of f with respect to X
is equal to Lambda / 6 * 2x
right
or
Lambda Lambda X over
3 what does that say that says that the
X component of force is proportional to
X
pushing away well depending on the sign
of Lambda and I had I kept my sign
straight we would have gotten it right
it's telling me that there's a component
of force along the radial
Direction the X component of force is
proportional to X the Y component of
force is proportional to
y and so it corresponds to everything in
the universe being pushed away from the
center by a Force proportional to the
distance and also proportional to the
cosmological constant now you might ask
wait a minute is there a special Center
the answer is no Force law like this
where everything is being pushed away
from everything else if you sat at the
center you would see everything being
pushed away but if you sat on one of the
particles that was being pushed
away you would also see the original
origin being pushed away from U so in
fact it's a force law which really
doesn't have a
center uh it really just corresponds to
everything what it corresponds to is
everything
expanding everything growing and the
separation between all objects uh
accelerating
outward so that's the cosmological
constant and Newton should have
discovered it it shouldn't have taken
Einstein Newton should have discovered
it well of course or maybe llas or maybe
Pon or whoever it was
who invented uh this kind of equation
here they could have discovered it it
was a possible thing in the
equations uh they
didn't but Einstein realized that there
was an ambiguity in the equations and he
for a while he entertained this now
notice you can put it on the other side
of the
equation minus
Lambda G muu
and you can therefore think of it as
part of the energy momentum tensor it's
a part of the energy momentum tensor
which is there even if nothing else is
there and so
sometimes the the
um uh the cosmological constant is a
little bit schizophrenic it doesn't know
which side of the equation it wants to
be on you can think of it as being on
the left side of the equation in which
case it's part of the geometry side of
of the
equation or you can put it on the right
hand side of the
equation in which case you can think of
it as vacuum energy energy that's there
when there's nothing else present you
can either think of it as a uniform
distribution of mass or negative mass or
positive depending on the sign of things
which is pushing things
out
uh in other words a funny form of energy
or you can include it on the left hand
side as a funny piece in uh in the
geometry side of the equations that's up
to
you
matter
yeah yeah neutal that's right but it's
numerical value in the real world is
extremely small why is it so how do we
know it's small it doesn't have any
influence on anything astronomically
until the distance remember it's a force
which grows with
distance it only
becomes measurable and and
detectable when the distance is out a
billion light years a couple of billion
light years then it becomes detectable
yeah my understanding was that if it was
Zero that or put it another way that he
introduced it because if it wasn't
present then he wouldn't then the uh
Universe wouldn't that his equation
didn't have a static that's right that's
right that's right
um yeah but that there he did make a
mistake
um the uh here's what he said he said
look the universe has been sitting here
for a long time why isn't everything
crushing in why isn't gravity pulling
all the stars together and stuff there's
got to be some compensating repulsive
Force so he introduced the uh the
cosmological constant as a
repulsion which would counteract uh the
attraction due to
gravity and it was possible using the
two of them together uh to create a
equilibrium where the repulsive effect
of the cosmological constant would
cancel the attractive effect of gravity
for the right for just the right magnet
it required a very delicate
cancellation uh cosmological constant
had to be just right but what he didn't
realize was that it was an un stable
equilibrium that uh that it was an
unstable and not a stable
equilibrium H sort of an
Armistice well it wasn't a very an
Armistice it was a bad Armistice because
it had the equil had stability problems
it was like you discover a rock hovering
above the Earth somewhere what do you
conclude you conclude there must be some
additional Force to grab gravity which
is holding the Rock from falling so you
invent a linear
force uh which pushes The Rock away and
there's some equilibrium point where the
attraction of gravity and the repulsion
of um of this new Force creates an
equilibrium now let's let's look at it
for a minute it's
interesting gravity is attractive
right let's plot the potential energy
let's imagine here's here's a imagine
here's the Earth here's a rock the rock
is noticed it's not hovering because of
centrifugal force it just hovers there
must be some repulsive Force that's
keeping it from falling toward the Earth
let's suppose it's of this kind of this
cosmological constant kind so that it
has a so that it has a force which is
proportional to distance can everybody
read that Force proportional to
distance okay let's plot the potential
energy first of all there's the
potential energy of the rock due to the
lump due to the Earth what does that
look
like potential
energy positive or
negative negative so it looks
like
this oops like that now supposing this
is a repulsive
Force then there's a potential energy
associated with it what was that
potential energy look
like not a straight line the force is a
straight line the potential energy would
be a parabola but would be a parabola
going up or a parabola going
down not if it's a repulsive Force if
it's a repulsive Force remember things
push toward lower
energy it would look like this
now supposing your rock was right over
here would it be in
equilibrium it would be an equilibrium
what if you gave it a little bit of a
push this
way what if you gave it a little bit of
a push that way that's exactly the the
situation that Einstein created by
balancing the cosmological constant
against ordinary gravity I don't know
whether he noticed it or not uh
it may be that he didn't notice that it
was unstable it may have been that he
noticed it was unstable and didn't care
or but uh but um he regarded it as his
most foolish
blunder but of course it was far from a
blunder there really is a cosmological
constant what was a blunder was the idea
that it could be used to keep the
Universe um uh in equilibrium that was
false but the idea that there should and
could be such a cosmological constant in
the equations that uh that is certainly
true yeah suppose that the cosmological
constant acted as an attractive force
would that produce a specific
origin no it would still be the same
that there's no specific origin but what
it would do it would it would enhance
the effect of gravity on pulling things
together and it would just create a
crun why wouldn't the forces all act to
direct it toward a specific
origin there's no specific origin
but we'll come to that that's why we're
going to be studying
cosmology so that we can understand the
geometry of a
world with such
forces but without a center we'll come
to that
but not so ni is it is it possible if
the entire universe could be spinning
and centripetal forces causing things to
fly
apart no
um first of all we know experimentally
that there's no uh that there's no um
axis of rotation just
observationally uh but even if there was
some rotational axis when you go far
enough out the universe can't be
rotating with any very significant
angular velocity why imagine it had a
fixed angular velocity when you go out
far enough it will be exceeding the
speed of light so you couldn't have a
global uniform Universe which was all in
uh in
rotation uh at best you could have some
small region in rotation and of course
you do they're called
galaxies are
but the Galaxy cannot act like an axis
which drags everything else with it just
because of the speed of light
constraint unless of course the rotation
is so small that even out at the edges
of the visible Universe the velocity is
still so small that it's well below the
speed of light but that would really be
observationally extremely small the uh
the angular frequency would be unique
place here too would we would be unique
wouldn't we if if
yes yeah then that would Place us the
Cent oh
good self
Center uh going back to the energy
momentum tensor can you talk about the
consequences of the off diagonal
terms
uh yeah
um I don't want to do that too much
right now they create sheer forces and
they create um they're for example very
instrumental in creating gravitational
waves gravitational waves are kind of
sheer waves uh we haven't talked about
them very much uh I'm not going to talk
about them tonight but uh yeah they know
they're extremely important in uh
creating gravitational
radiation um I'm not sure what to say
about
them
uh but for examp you know there's no
difference
incidentally
between here is two things which sound
entirely different take a block of
material and try to Shear
it yeah so here it is we take a block of
material and we push this Edge this way
and that edge that way um making
sure
well let's say we hold this Edge down on
the floor glue it to the floor and push
the top that creates some stress inside
the
block now here's something that sounds
entirely different take the block
squeeze it this way and stretch it this
way in fact they're identical to each
other except rotated by
45° it's not hard to convince yourself
that if you think about it a little bit
that that a squeezing this way and a
stretching this way is the same as a
Shear along a 45 degree axis right so
what this
means is that off diagonal
elements are the same as having on
diagonal Elements which are different
from each
other for example a positive and a
negative on diagonal element in any case
um we we'll come we'll come back to that
uh sheer and so forth it is important it
does have all sorts of consequences but
uh it's it's not a good time for it
now uh requires a little more
explanation yeah is there is there an
intuitive solution of these equations
that sort of describes a planet going
around a sun that will give us a a
little bit of sense of you know the the
meaning of the of the the different
metrics and you know what would be
well okay um the easy thing to do is to
work and we're going to do it it's not
that easy but the easier thing to do is
to solve the equations of gravity when
the right hand side here is just a
spherical Mass the sun we can solve it
we can find the metric we can calculate
all the chopal symbols and we can
calculate the motion of a small planet
traveling around the Sun absolutely the
solution is called The schat Shield
solution and it's the solution of a
radially symmetric uh Mass uh outside
the mass that's what that's what we're
going to do we're going to study that
solution uh and it is also the solution
of a black
hole uh the problem of solving
Einstein's equations for two masses both
of which are big enough to create a
significant gravitational field
you don't want to know I mean that's a
that's a job that's a job for
supercomputer not for uh for human
equation
solving so yeah it's kind of intrigued
with the idea of U energy momentum
censure for light being uh uh very large
and then so that skew beams would would
uh light light beams going past each
other would you around each other you do
that much better than I do you do that
much better than I do do it again do it
again it
again now you're on
the but anyway doesn't that sort of
imply that you could indeed have a high
enough energy light density so
that go in a complete circle the way it
does inside the short shell radius well
what I said was not that light has a a
big energy momentum tensor I said it has
a very small energy momentum
tensor yeah but okay but small because
there are C4s in the denominator or C
squares in the denom denominator but in
principle could you still
have
uh so all right so you're asking the
question bound a ring of light or
something like
that bound to what
though going in going in the r going in
a circle
for example around the around the
star maybe a black hole made out of
photons yeah um you you could certainly
have a um a light wave going around the
circular orbit around the black hole the
trouble is the um the circular
orbit uh of a light Ray is
unstable again it's a unstable orbit so
if it's
if you have a
mass a given mass and you consider a
circular orbit at a certain distance
then the velocity of that circular orbit
is fixed by The Distance by the
parameters of the mass and the distance
so for example the Earth's distance from
the Sun determines its
velocity as you come in closer to the pl
to the star or whatever it is the Vel
velocity gets larger if you have a real
genuine black hole you can get in close
enough to it not so not so close that
you're
trapped uh about uh three schwart Shield
radi away from it where there's a closed
orbit of a light
Ray in other words a closed orbit where
the velocity is equal to the speed of
light
um so there's one particular orbital
distance where a circular
uh light Ray circular light circular
path a lightlike circular path can exist
the problem is if it deviates just a
little bit in toward then it gets sucked
in and if it deviates a little bit
outward it goes out so it's an unstable
orbit so there's an unstable um orbit
for a light Ray outside of black
hole
there one at time if you were there
would you just see
on that you would just see a plane
instead of the actual a plane you mean
like an airplane mean the Sur the
surface of the star would be would look
like a
plane you're in that circular orbit if
you were on that circular orbit yeah
well it would be a light you
don't you wouldn't see you wouldn't see
the any curvature seeing the starage
look
like well I'm not sure that I'm not sure
that the that the light beams see
anything I have to think I would have to
think about what a very fast Observer
moving around on close to that light R
would see no say say you didn't have to
go as fast as light but I'm just at that
distance then what it would look like is
it if you're at that distance being
supported and kept from falling into the
black hole you would just see in front
of you a great big Horizon
black flat plane the surface of the star
would flat plane oh well not
quite the this this orbit is not quite
at the Horizon it's
uh The Horizon is uh it's three halves
times the distance to the Horizon to be
precise but I'm not look when we get to
the geometry of black holes you will
understand the great deal about black
holes that you don't understand now and
you'll understand just how foolish your
questions have been up till
now that's my goal
[Music]
to
okay
yeah
um for uh they
do for example
the sums of the the sums of the space
like igen values divided by three is the
pressure
um the time like igen value is related
to the um uh to the energy density in a
frame of reference moving with the fluid
if it happens to be a
fluid
uh if the igen values of the space you
know it has four igen values one in a
Tim like Direction
uh three and space likee directions if
the three space likee igen values are
all equal it means that in some frame of
reference the fluid if let's think of it
as a fluid is
isotropic
uh if they're different it means that
there are some sheer forces or or
squeezing and
stretching so yes they they definitely
do have
meaning um
I mean they they basically characterize
the uh uh the State of Affairs
Yeah question yeah the if you have an
isolated mass in space then you do you
adjust
the um the remon tensor so that it's uh
so the curvature is zero at Infinity yes
then how do you do that with a
cosmological concept you
don't no good if you have a
cosmologic excuse
me if you have a cosmological
constant then the geometry that's
associated with it is not flat at
Infinity it's what's called deit space
or anti deit space and it's an entirely
different kind of
geometry so the answer is if there's a
cosmological constant you don't adjust
the geometry so that the remont tensor
is zero far away in fact if you have a
cosmological
constant yeah okay let's uh let's go
back let's
see if we have a cosmological constant
then we can set this equal to Lambda G
mu no I may have changed the sign of
Lambda but it doesn't
matter okay now let's contract this
equation with G mu new
this becomes
R this becomes minus 2
R and what does this
[Music]
become four Lambda
right h four
Lambda so we find that minus
r is equal to four or Lambda is equal to
or R is equal to - 4 Lambda in other
words even if there's no matter around
if all there is is cosmological constant
then out to Infinity the curvature
scalar is exactly given by the
cosmological
constant uh if there is no matter around
and only this then one would say that
um that space is space and space time
are uniformly curved uniformly curved
because the remon scaler is uniform
everywhere just given by the
cosmological constant so um I forgot
what the question was but I think I
answered
it in all of this are we assuming that
the the universe is infinite
no no so we could have a model of a of a
finite Universe even with the
cosmological con
no now yes you can have a model of one
question is you know real honest physics
would physics when everything is taken
into account what can you expect that's
uh that's debatable but yes you can have
a closed Universe with a cosmological
constant do we know enough now to
understand what frame gring
is no not yet no I think we need to um
well we we
need no not yet not yet not yet do we
know enough to understand what it is
whether the universe is flat or
not um space time is flat or space is
flat space time is flat means it's just
absolutely empty and there is no energy
or momentum because if there were it
just wouldn't be flat Lo but univ at
Infinity yes it just means that uh yes
it means that the geometry or the metric
can be taken to just go to Adu far
away that's all it means and it would be
exactly the situation Whenever there are
some concentrated
masses that create gravitational fields
that fall off far
away then SpaceTime is as totically flat
is the right
terminology ASM totically flat just
means that the components of the
metric uh ASM totically tend to adom you
new but it's not obvious that that's
true because there's investigation me in
the real world in the real world it's
not
true it's most definitely not true found
to be closer and closer what's that
investigation has shown that it's very
very close to being no no you're
confusing the curvature of space with
the temperature of space time okay okay
that's why I asked you do you mean space
or space time right yeah we can um I
don't know how much we're going to get
into that this quarter and how much
we'll save it for next
quarter uh but flat space and flat space
time are two quite different
things we will go through the Schwarz
Shield black
hole and the schwart shield metric and
um and if I have time a little bit about
the expanding uh universe but I think it
will take a full two hours to uh to
navigate through the Schwarz Shield
metric and really that's kind of the
goal you know that's that's that's the
real thing so I don't want to stop
before we do the schw show metric right
okay so next week we no yeah next week
yeah
[Music]
the proceeding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu